Guide to the Woodson Research Center art collection, 1912 - 2012 UA 063
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Woodson Research Center art collection
1912-2012
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University.
UA 063
68 Linear Feet
This collection consists of framed paintings, framed and unframed drawings, prints, sculptures, and other artworks donated to the Woodson Research Center/Rice University archives.
Biographical / Historical
The Woodson Research Center art collection has been accumulated over the years since the Rice Institute opened in 1912 with donations from Rice University and from Rice alumni. The collection mostly consists of items directly related to the history of Rice University, the Fondren Library, and the Woodson Research Center. Much of the collection is displayed in the Fondren Library in the Woodson Research Center; the remainder is stored onsite in the library.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of framed paintings,framed and unframed drawings, prints, sculptures, and other artworks donated to the Woodson Research Center/Rice University archives.
Conditions Governing Access
These materials are open for research. Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center, Fondren Library.
Index Terms
Subjects
Sculpture, American
Document Types
prints (visual works); paintings (visual works); drawings (visual works)
Places
Art
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University.
- Series I: Art displayed in the Woodson Research Center, Fondren Library
  - Edgar Odell Lovett, bronze maquette, 1912; Wolfe, Bruce, 1941- (Item 1)
  - Edgar Odell Lovett, bronze bust, 2012; Wolfe, Bruce, 1941- (Item 2)
  - William Ward Watkin, bronze bust, 1938; McVey, William M. (Item 3)
  - Benjamin N. (Woody) Woodson, bronze bust, c. 1960's; Unknown (Item 4)
  - Mary Ellen Hale Lovett, oil painting, c. 1924; Leroux, Auguste, 1871-1954 (Item 5)
    Biographical / Historical
    Mary Hale Lovett was the wife of Edgar Odell Lovett, first President of the Rice Institute.
  - Great Horned Owl, print copy of Audubon engraving, 1829; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851 (Item 6)
    General
    This is a printed copy of the engraving from Birds of America. Date of the printed copy is unknown.
    Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
  - Lovett Hall, painting/collage, 1961; Condon, Bill, 1923-1998 (Item 7)
  - French Village, oil painting, c. 1917; Browne, Frederic William, 1877-1966 (Item 8)
  - Herself, oil painting, c. 1950s; John, Grace Spaulding, 1890-1972 (Item 9)
  - Pecos Valley, color woodcut print, 1921; Baumann, Gustave, 1881-1971 (Item 10)
  - Fondren Library, watercolor, 1952; Schiwetz, Edward Muegge (Schiwetz, Edward (Buck) Muegge), 1898-1984 (Item 11)
  - Eye of an owl, photograph, 2008; Lovell, Rick (Item 12)
  - Administration Building, Approach from Main Street, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 13)
  - First class of the Rice Institute, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 14)
  - Formal Opening: Residential Hall scene, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 15)
  - Mechanical Laboratory and Power Plant, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 16)
  - Residential Hall construction, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 17)
  - Administration Building and Formal Opening, lecture in the Faculty Chamber, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 18)
  - Academic Court, toward Main Street, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 19)
  - Administration Building:Exterior Elevation, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 20)
  - Administration Building-Cloister, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 21)
  - Administration Building- Column Detail, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 22)
  - Alice Crowell Dean, oil painting, 1925; Tidden, John Clark (Item 23)
    Alice Dean was a member of the Rice Institute class of 1916, and the first Librarian at Rice.
- Series II: Art pieces in storage
  - Professor Senator Vito Volterra, ink drawing, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Lovett Hall, print, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chemistry Building Construction Scene, watercolor, 1924; Chillman, James H., Jr., 1886-1952 (Item 24)
  - Gardens of Doria Palace, Genoa, watercolor, 1922; Chillman, James H., Jr., 1886-1952 (Item 25)
  - Margaret Bremond Rice, oil painting, Unknown (Item 26)
  - Frederic Allyn Rice, oil painting, 1908; Gordon, Boris B. (Item 27)
  - WIlliam Marsh Rice as a young man, copy of oil painting, Unknown (Item 28)
  - Margarett Root Brown, oil painting, Unknown (Item 29)
  - Lovett Hall, framed print, 1978; Besselman, Steven, 1950-1988 (Item 30)
  - W. M. Rice, founder of the Wm. M. Rice Institute, steel engraving (2), E. G. Williams & Bro., NY (Item 31-32)
  - Print from an original oil painting of W.M. Rice at the age of 34 years (Item 33)
  - Formal opening of the Rice Institute, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 34)
  - Trustees and first faculty of the Rice Institute, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 35)
  - Formal opening: President Lovett delivering inaugural address, photograph, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 36)
  - Formal opening: Delegates and visitors, 1912-2005; E. W. Irish Photo Co. (Item 37)